<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>SCBdo Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>SCBdo povides a collection of utilities for cycle race timing
            and data handling.</para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Nathan Fraser</holder>
    </copyright>

    <authorgroup>
      <author role="maintainer">
        <firstname>Nathan</firstname>
        <surname>Fraser</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>SCBdo Manual</revnumber>
        <date>2010-11-06</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version 1.2.8 of SCBdo</releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>SCBdo povides a collection of utilities for cycle race timing
        and data handling.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>SCBdo is a collection of utilities and modules to manage
          electronic timing and data handling for cycle races. It also
          includes abstract interfaces for Alge Timy, Times-7 Wheeltime
          and Omega Scoreboard hardware.</para>
    <para>Top level applications are provided for mass start road
          races, and track meets.
    </para>
    <para>This manual covers basic usage of the roadmeet and trackmeet
          programs. For
          detailed information on modules, check the internal program
          documentation with pydoc.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Roadrace</title>
    <para>Timing, data handling and scoreboard for road races.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>Roadrace provides some simple tools for generating a road
            race result. It tracks riders across a finish line with
            messages from a Times7 wheeltime and allows full override
            of places and bunch times.</para>
      <para>The program is intended to be used alongside manual systems
            for judging, timekeeping and officiating.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Setup</title>
      <para>Preparation for a race involves allocation of rider numbers,
            creation of a start list, addition of sponsor logos if required
            and synchronisation with the Times7 clock.</para>
      <para>Roadrace is still very much beta software so the preparation
            involves the following somewhat clunky steps:</para>
      <para>1: Open roadrace and select Meet-&gt;Open. Select
            &quot;Create Folder&quot;, choose a name for the project, then
            select &quot;Open&quot;. This will create a new blank road
            meet. Fill in the basic event details by selecting
            Meet-&gt;Properties. If you plan on printing reports,
            select the Print Properties option and choose a preferred
            printer. Then close the program.</para>
      <para>2: Edit the rider &quot;database&quot; by opening the file
            riders.csv in the directory you created. Once all rider names
            and numbers are loaded, save the file and re-start roadrace.
            Open your race with Meet-&gt;Open, the newly added riders
            will now appear under the riders tab.
            </para>
      <para>3: Select the race action &quot;Add starters&quot; from the
            action combo box, then enter your starters in the field
            provided. Once all rider numbers are in, hit enter to load the
            race result. At this point a start list can be printed from the
            reports menu if required.</para>
      <para>3a: (optional) If sponsor logos are required on reports, 
            add the files logo.jpg, sublogo.jpg and footer.jpg to your
            event folder. These images will be placed on all printed
            reports in the top left, top right and bottom of each page
            (respectively).</para>
      <para>4: Do a rough synchronisation with the Times7 box if required
            then clear its memory from the timing menu. The program is now
            ready to run a race.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Running a race</title>
      <para>Hit F5 to arm the system for a start trigger, or manually
            enter the race start time using the edit times button in
            the result tab. Once running an elapsed time will be displayed
            and the status button will show 'Running'. </para>
      <para>As riders come past the finish area, they will be displayed
            in the scratch pad. This view shows a count of riders,
            a count of riders in the bunch, the RFtime and down time on
            the first person in the list. To clear the scratch pad,
            hit F6 (eg for the start of a new lap). During this time 
            it is possible to query the status of a rider using the 
            query rider action, or by typing the number into the result
            pane.</para>
      <para>Riders that did not start or those that abandon can be
            registered by selecting the appropriate action from the
            race action option and then entering their rider numbers.
            DNF and DNS actions will be logged and can be reversed if
            required later.</para>
      <para>When the riders are about to finish, hit F9 to 'arm' the
            system for finish. Once armed, all riders crossing the finish
            area will record a finish time and the result will start to
            arrange itself. At this stage, it is possible to produce
            a judges report for confirmation of places with the judges.
            To temporarily disable recording of finishers, hit F9 to toggle
            between running and finish.</para>
      <para>Once all riders are in or accounted for, hit F10 to cease
            recording. Places can then be entered manually, or they 
            can be rearranged using the F7/F8 mark and promote method
            (documented below). After putting riders in the correct order,
            it may be necessary to adjust bunch times for some riders.
            Once that is done, the result can be examined with the result
            report.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Adjusting places with Mark/Promote</title>
      <para>When confirming places with the judges, most of the riders
            that cross the line will be in the correct order. For those
            that are not, there is a shorthand keyboard method to quickly
            scan and correct the full list of places.</para>
      <para>As the judges list of places is read out, scroll down the 
            result list with the keyboard. When you get to a place that
            is not correct press F7 to 'mark' the current place in the
            result, then type in the bib of the next placed rider, or
            scroll to the desired record. Once
            that rider is found, press F8 to 'promote' the selected rider
            into the position previously marked.</para>
      <para>After a 'promotion', the places upto that point will be filled
            in automatically.</para>
      <para>If there is a dead heat for any places, it must be entered
            manually in the race action entry. Type the bib of each 
           place separated with spaces, and use a minus character to
           separate riders that were awarded the same place.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Results</title>
      <para>Final results can be printed directly from the reports menu
            or exported for use with other programs. The format of the
            result export will most likely change over time.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Trackmeet</title>
    <para>Timing, data handling and scoreboard for track race meets.</para>
  </section>
</article>
